Hello everyone, Icon Finder
is a multimodal search system featuring
four specialized modes: ‘Match’
finds assets
via uploaded icon screenshots.
‘Describe’ leverages
semantic search to locate
icons based on your natural language
descriptions.
‘Keyword’ provides
precise, tag-based retrieval.
Finally, ‘Usage’ locates
how specific icons
are implemented within real product UIs.
The left panel offers global filtering
across
Spectrum design system
versions and product lines.
The central workspace
supports drag-and-drop
or direct input to instantly initiate
your search.
Upon uploading an icon screenshot,
the system instantly retrieves
visual matches.
To streamline browsing,
results are intelligently grouped
by unique asset name.
The purple badge on a card indicates
the total number of variants
within that specific asset group.
On the left panel,
you can further narrow down your results.
Use the ‘Style’ section
to filter by asset type,
or utilize the ‘Category’
section which is powered by underlying
icon tags for
precise, metadata-driven refinement.
Selecting a result opens
the detail view in the right-side
panel,
presenting specific asset information.
A key feature here is the ‘Icon
in action’ section.
This provides immediate,
real-world context by showcasing
actual product screenshots—across
applications like Animate, Express,
and Creative Cloud—where
this exact icon is currently deployed.
Clicking a product screenshot launches
an expanded
Lightbox view for precise spatial context.
Observe
the prominent orange bounding boxes.
These immediately pinpoint exactly
where the asset is implemented
within the complex UI.
Furthermore, the system
automatically identifies and highlights
every instance of the icon
across the entire screen, simultaneously
returning to the detail panel.
Expanding the resources
section reveals direct
handoff integrations for designers.
Figma deep links route
you instantly to the exact asset
within the official icon library file.
For developers upcoming integration
with A4U.
Our internal Artifactory service
will bridge the gap from design to code,
allowing you to directly retrieve
the corresponding NPM packages
straight from this interface.
Finally, let's explore
the usage search mode
by simply entering a text description
like crop image.
The engine scans our entire database
of recorded product screenshots.
It directly returns the exact image crops
of matching icons found in real
UI environments.
Selecting a result opens
the source interface in the Lightbox view.
Here, the prominent orange bounding
box pinpoints
the icons exact coordinates on the screen,
giving you immediately
indisputable context of how
the asset is implemented in production.
This search paradigm
extends far beyond icons.
Moving forward,
this same architecture will scale to power
the discovery of complex illustrations
and comprehensive UI patterns.
By bridging past implementations
with future design concepts, it
empowers designers
with immediate inspiration while ensuring
a seamlessly consistent
look and feel across
our entire product ecosystem.
The audio is automatically generated
synthesized
by an AI model solely
to demonstrate the new features.